有些鱼是永远抓不到的
There are some fish that cannot be caught.
这不是因为它们游的快或者比其他鱼强壮
It's not that they're faster or stronger than other fish.
而是他们有些与众不同
They're just touched by something extra.
这条鱼叫野兽
One such fish was The Beast.
在我出生的那个时候他已经是个传奇人物了
And by the time I was born he was already a legend.
他在阿拉巴马使鱼饵落空的次数比其他鱼多100次
He'd passed up more $ 100 lures than any fish in Alabama.
有人说这条鱼...
Some said that fish was the ghost of a thief...
是那个60年前在这条湖里淹死的小偷的亡灵
...who'd drowned in that river 60 years before.
另外的人说他是白垩纪的恐龙
Others claimed he was a dinosaur left over from the "Cruaceous" Period.
我对这种假设或者迷信不屑一顾
I didn't put any stock into such speculation or superstition.
我曾经抓住过这条鱼...
All I knew was I'd been trying to catch that fish...
...在我还没你大的时候
...since I was a boy no bigger than you.
在你出生的那天....
And on the day you were born...
就是我抓住他的那天
Well, that was the day I finally caught him.
现在  我要尝试所有的方法:
Now, I'd tried everything on it:
虫子   诱饵   花生白脱   还有奶酪
Worms, lures, peanut butter, peanut butter and cheese.
但是在那天我得到了个启示:
But on that day I had a revelation:
如果那条鱼是亨利.华斯的灵魂
If that fish was Henry Walls' ghost,
一般的诱饵是起不了作用的
then the usual bait wasn't gonna work.
我一定要用他最想得到的东西做诱饵
I was gonna have to use something he truly desired.
-你的手指? -黄金
- Your finger? - Gold.
现在   我把戒指系上了他们做的线...
Now, I tied my ring onto the strongest line they made...
...据他们说结实的在短短几分钟可以拉起一座桥
...strong enough to hold up a bridge, they said, if only for a few minutes.
然后我在上游投出了
And then I cast upriver.
那个怪物跳了起来  甚至还没等到接触水面就抓住了它
The Beast jumped up and grabbed it before it even hit the water.
然后非常迅速地折断了那条线
And just as fast, he snapped clean through that line.
你明白我的窘境了吧
Well, you can see my predicament.
我的结婚戒指   忠实於我妻子的标志...
My wedding ring, the symbol of fidelity to my wife...
-...她马上要成为我孩子的妈妈了... -让他停下来
...soon to be mother of my child... - Make him stop.
...现在已经在一条抓不到的鱼的肠子里了
...was now lost in the gut of an uncatchable fish.
你是怎么做的?
What did you do?
我从上游跟那个条鱼到下游
I followed that fish upriver and downriver.
那条鱼   那个怪物...
This fish, The Beast...
...我们一直称它为"他"   但是实际上应该是"她"
...the whole time we were calling it a him, when in fact it was a her.
它正怀着孩子  随时可能临产
It was fat with eggs it was gonna lay any day.
现在我就处在这种情况中
Now, I was in a situation.
我要割开那条鱼的肚子把我的结婚戒指取回来...
I could gut that fish and get my wedding ring back...
...但如果我这么做了
...but in doing so I'd
就等於杀死了阿斯顿湖里最聪明的鱼
be killing the smartest catfish in the Ashton River.
我要剥夺...
Did I want to deprive my son the chance...
...我的子孙抓住这条鱼的机会吗?
...to catch a fish like this of his own?
我和那条鱼夫人....
This ladyfish and I...
-我们有着相同的使命 -"我们都是相同等式的一部分"
- Well, we had the same destiny. - "We were part of the same equation."
现在  你也许会问...
Now, you may well ask...
哦   亲爱的   亲爱的   这是你的夜晚
Oh, darling, darling, it's still your night.
...为什么对其他东西都无动於衷的它对金子下手那么快?
...why did it strike so quick on gold when nothing else would attract it?
那是从那天的事我学到的...
That was the lesson I learned that day...
...我儿子出生的那天
...the day my son was born.
有时抓住一个女人的心的唯一方法...
Sometimes the only way to catch an uncatchable woman...
...就是给她一个结婚戒指
...is to offer her a wedding ring.
什么   父亲竟然不能和儿子说话?
What, a father's not allowed to talk about his son?
在这个故事里我是个註解   爸爸...
I'm a footnote in that story, Dad...
...你这个奇遇从来就没有发生过
...the context for your great adventure, which never happened, incidentally.
在我出生的时候你在威齐塔卖气货
You were selling novelty products in Wichita when I was born.
来吧   威尔. 每个人都喜欢这个故事!
Come on, Will. Everyone loves that story!
不是的. 我就不喜欢.已经听了几千遍了!
They don't. I don't love that story. Not anymore. Not after a thousand times!
我知道每个要点   父亲 我能像那样再说一遍了!
I know every punch line, Dad. I can tell them as well as you can!
一个晚上   我生命中的一个晚上...
For one night, one night in your entire life...
...宇宙不再绕着爱德华.布鲁旋转
...the universe did not revolve around Edward Bloom.
-你为什么不能理解呢? -很抱歉麻烦你了
- How can you not understand that? - I'm sorry to embarrass you.
你在烦你自己   爸爸. 只是你自己不知道
You're embarrassing yourself, Dad. You just don't see it.
那晚以后  我三年没有再和我父亲说过话
After that night, I didn't speak to my father again for three years.
威廉.布鲁   联合国际报. 如果我能--
William Bloom, United Press International. If I could just...
我想我们可以间接地沟通
We communicated indirectly, I guess.
在她的信和圣诞卡里   我妈妈写信给她们两个
In her letters and Christmas cards, my mother wrote for both of them.
我打电话去的时候
And when I'd call,
她总是说父亲驾车出去了 或者是在游泳池里游泳
she'd say Dad was out driving or swimming in the pool.
就这样   我们再也没有说话
True to form, we never talked about not talking.
实际上   我没有在我父亲身上看到我
The truth is, I didn't see anything of myself in my father.
我相信他也没在我身上找到他的影子
And I don't think he saw anything of himself in me.
我们就像相互瞭解的陌生人
We were like strangers who knew each other very well.
说起我父亲这一生的故事...
In telling the story of my father's life...
...很难把事实和虚幻分开
...it's impossible to separate fact from fiction,
他是一个有着传奇色彩的人物
the man from the myth.
最好的办法是我把他告诉我的複述出来
The best I can do is to tell it the way he told me.
故事不一定合理   可能大多数没有发生过
It doesn't always make sense, and most of it never happened.
把我的戒指还给我!
Give me back my ring!
谢谢!
Thank you!
但是这种故事就是这样的
But that's what kind of story this is.
他的出生便为他以后的生活打下了基础
His birth would set the pace for his unlikely life.
没有比大多数人活的长   但是伟大
No longer than most men's, but larger.
他的故事越离奇...
And as strange as his stories got...
... 故事的结局就越出人意料
...the endings were always the most surprising of all.
对. 对   他在这
Yes. Yes, he's here.
是你母亲
It's your mother.
本耐特医生怎么说?
And what does Dr. Bennett say?
不  当然  我要他听电话
No, sure, I'll talk to him.
好  我等
Yeah, I'll wait.
情况不好?
It's bad?
对   比他们想像的还糟 他们要停止化疗
Yeah, it's more than they thought. They're gonna stop chemo.
-你要去一次. -可能今晚
- You need to go. - Probably tonight.
-我和你一起去. -不   不   不. 不行
- I'm going with you. - No, no, no. You shouldn't.
我和你一起去
I'm going with you.
现在  你要听哪个故事?
Now, which one's it gonna be?
"穀仓里的猴子" 还是 "路边的狗"?
"Monkey in a Barn," or "Dog in the Road"?
有女巫的那个
The one about the witch.
-你会做恶梦的. -但是我不怕
- You get nightmares. - But I'm not scared.
一开始我也不会
Well, neither was I, at first.
这个故事发生在阿斯顿的郊外
Now, this took place in the swamp outside of Ashton.
因为有蛇  孩子们不能去那   蜘蛛...
Children weren't allowed in the swamp on account of the snakes, spiders...
...和流沙会在你尖叫前把你卷进去
...and quicksand that would swallow you up before you could even scream.
那天晚上我们有5个人:
There were five of us out there that night:
我   露西   威尔博.布利...
Me, Ruthie, Wilbur Freely...
...和普来斯兄弟   丹和扎奇
...and the Price Brothers, Don and Zacky.
没人知道那里有什么
And not one of us knew what was in store.
大家都知道有一定规模的 城镇大多会有一个女巫...
It's common knowledge that most towns of a certain size have a witch...
...会吃那些不听话的小孩...
...if only to eat misbehaving children...
...还有在她园子里散步的小狗
...and the occasional puppy who wanders into her yard.
女巫用这些骨头来施魔法和诅咒...
Witches use those bones to cast spells and curses...
...让土地变的荒芜
...and make the land infertile.
她有一个玻璃眼球是不是真的?
Is it true she got a glass eye?
我听说他是吉普赛人
I heard she got it from gypsies.
-吉普赛人是干什么的? -你妈妈是吉普赛人
- What's a gypsy? - Your momma's a gypsy.
你妈妈是个贱女人
Your momma's a bitch.
有女士在场你不能骂人
You shouldn't swear. There's ladies present.
-妈的 -见鬼
- Shit. - Damn.
疯子 把你的手电关了. 她会看见你的!
Screw.Turn off your flashlights. She'll see you!
然而在阿拉巴马州的所有女巫中...
Yet of all the witches in Alabama...
...有一个女巫据说是最可怕的
...there was one who was said to be the most feared.
因为她有一只玻璃眼睛  据说有着神秘的魔力
For she had one glass eye which was said to contain mystical powers.
如果你看见了   就会知道自己是怎么死的
I heard if you look right at it, you'll see how you're gonna die.
简直是胡说   他不是个真正的芜师
That's bull-S-H-l-T, that is. She's not even a real witch.
如果你肯定   就去把那个眼睛拿来
If you're so sure, go get that eye.
我听说她把眼睛藏在床头柜里. 你是不是怕啦?
I heard she keeps it in a box on her night table. Or are you too scared?
我现在就去拿
I'll go in right now and get that eye.
-去啊. -好   我会的
- Then do it. - Fine, I will.
-好   你去 -好   现在就去
- Fine, you do it. - Fine, I'm doing it.
爱德华   不要!
Edward, don't!
她会把你变成肥皂的. 她经常会这么做
She'll make soap out of you. That's what she does.
把人变成肥皂
She makes soap out of people.
夫人   我叫爱德华.布鲁...
Ma'am, my name is Edward Bloom...
...有些人要看看你的眼睛
...and there's some folks like to see your eye.
-那拿到那个了? -我带来了
- You get The Eye? - I brought it.
让我们看看
Let's see it.
哇   救命!
Whoa, help!
我看见自己怎么死的了. 我摔下来  不行了
I saw how I was gonna die. I was old and I fell.
我一点也不老
I wasn't old at all.
我成天想着死. 看见了自己是怎么死的
I was thinking about death and all. About seeing how you're gonna die.
我的意思是   一方面   如果你想的都是死...
I mean, on one hand, if dying was all you thought about...
...它就会搅乱你的生活
...it could kind of screw you up.
但是这对你也是一种帮助   不是吗?
But it could kind of help you, couldn't it?
因为   其他的所有情况下   你知道你会得救
Because, everything else, you'd know you could survive.
我想说的是我想知道
I guess I'm saying I'd like to know.
我是怎么死的
That's how I go.
嗨   妈妈
Hi, Mom.
那是不是本耐特大夫的车?
Is that Dr. Bennett's car?
是的. 现在他和你父亲在上面
Yes. He's up with your father now.
-他怎么样? -不   我来吧
- And how is he? - Well... No, I got it.
他没救了. 不吃东西. 因为没吃东西  所以越来越虚弱
He's impossible. He won't eat. Because he doesn't eat, he's weaker.
因为他虚弱   所以就更吃不动
Because he's weak, he doesn't want to eat.
-他还剩多少日子? -你现在不能说这个
- How much time does he have left? - You don't talk about that.
还没到时间
Not yet.
威尔
Will.
本耐特大夫. 哦   很高兴见到你
Dr. Bennett. Oh, it's good to see you.
我的妻子   傑瑟芬
My wife, Josephine.
很荣幸见到你
A pleasure.
-有7个月了 -离那个日子!
- You're seven months. - To the day!
是个男孩
It's a boy.
试着让他喝点什么. 即使他不要也要试着让他喝
Try to get him to drink one of these. He won't, but go ahead and try.
爸爸?
Dad?
你要喝水?
You want some water?
-没想到你能来 -是吗?
- You are in for a surprise. - Am I?
有了孩子一切都改变了
Having a kid changes everything.
要裹尿布  打嗝  半夜喂奶
There's the diapers and the burping and the midnight feeding.
-你都做过吗? -没有
- Did you do any of that? - No.
我听说这很糟糕
But I hear it's terrible.
那你就教坏那个孩子让他误入歧途...
Then you spend years trying to corrupt and mislead this child...
...教他歪理   然而他却成长的很好
...fill its head with nonsense, and still it turns out perfectly fine.
-你认为我要去试试吗? -你已经跟最好的老师在学习了
- You think I'm up for it? - You learned from the best.
喝一半. 我会告诉你妈妈你全喝了
Drink half the can. I'll tell Mom you drank it all.
双赢
Everyone wins.
大家都不用操心. 还没到时间
People needn't worry so much. It's not my time yet.
我还不用走
This is not how I go.
-真的? -实际上. 我从那个眼睛里看到了
- Really? - Truly. I saw it in The Eye.
-沼泽旁的那个老女人? -她是个女巫
- The old lady by the swamp? - She was a witch.
不   她只是有点老
No, she was old and probably senile.
我从那只眼睛里看到我是怎么死的   但现在好像不是这样子
I saw my death in that eye, and this isn't how it happens.
应该是怎么样的呢?
So how does it happen?
奇怪的结局. 我不想破坏气愤
Surprise ending. Wouldn't want to ruin it for you.
你妈妈说你我没机会再说话了
Your mother thought we wouldn't talk again.
看看我们.现在聊的多好
Look at us. We're talking fine.
我们都是讲故事的人  我们两个
We're storytellers, both of us.
我说我的   你写你的. 一回事
I speak mine out, you write yours down. Same thing.
爸爸....
Dad...
我想在我在这的时候谈些事
I hope to talk about some things while I'm here.
你的意思是我在这
You mean while I'm here.
我只是想知道事情的真相:
I just want to know the true versions of things:
真实的事和编造的故事
Events. Stories.
你
You.
你妈妈没有保住游泳池
Your mother hasn't been keeping up the pool.
-如果你想做  你可以修一下 -恩   我会的
- lf you wanted to, you could fix it. - Yeah, I will.
-你知道化学药品在哪吗? -你出门的时候我做的
- You know where the chemicals are? - I did it when you were gone.
我从来不喜欢在家呆着   威尔. 太拘束了
I was never much for being at home, Will. Too confining.
然而现在   却被困在床上....
And this here, being stuck in bed...
等死是我一生中最糟糕的事
Dying is the worst thing that's ever happened to me.
-我想你说的是你不会死 -我说的不是我是怎么死的
- I thought you said you weren't dying. - I said this isn't how I go.
最后部分最不寻常
The last part is much more unusual.
相信我的话
Trust me on that.
本耐特大夫说我要在家呆一星期
Dr. Bennett said I have to stay at home for a week.
哦   没什么. 有一次   我在床上呆了3年
Oh, that's nothing. Once, I had to stay in bed for three years.
-是你得水痘的那次? -是就好了
- Did you have the chickenpox? - I wish.
事实上   没人知道那里出错了
Truth is, no one quite knew what was wrong.
一个人成长的大多数时间...
Most times a person grows up gradually...
...当我瞭解我自己的时候
...while I found myself in a hurry.
我的肌肉  我的骨骼   无法跟上我的身体猛长的速度
My muscles and my bones couldn't keep up with my body's ambition.
所以我在床上渡过了三年大好时光...
So I spent the better part of three years confined to my bed...
... 看百科全书是我唯一的探索方式
...with the encyclopedia being my only means of exploration.
我看到了G部...
I had made it all the way to the G's...
...想要找到"巨人症"的答案...
...hoping to find an answer to my "gigantificationism"...
... 当我翻开一篇关於金鱼的文章的时候
...when I uncovered an article about the common goldfish.
"放在一个小碗里   金鱼会变小
"Kept in a small bowl, the goldfish will remain small.
地方大了...
With more space...
...金鱼就会两倍三倍的长大"
...the fish will grow double, triple, or quadruple its size."
我似乎找到了我狂长的原因...
It occurred to me then that perhaps the reason for my growth...
...是因为我要做大事
...was that I was intended for larger things.
毕竟   伟大的人身躯都很魁梧
After all, a giant man can't have an ordinary-sized life.
直到我的骨骼发育成型...
As soon as my bones had settled in their adult configuration...
...我就开始计划在阿斯顿打开更广阔的天地
...I set upon my plan to make a bigger place for myself in Ashton.
老虎   走!
Tigers, go!
爱德华.布鲁!
Edward Bloom!
小狗! 我的小狗! 我的小狗被困住了!
Doggy! My doggy! My doggy's trapped!
这是我在阿斯顿看到最大的事件
I was the biggest thing Ashton had ever seen.
直到一天   一个陌生人来到这
Until one day, a stranger arrived.
冷静. 冷静   大家冷静. 已经够了
Calm down. Calm down, everybody. Calm down. That's enough.
-市长先生   他把玉米地吃遍了 -他吃了我的狗
- Mr. Mayor, he ate an entire corn field. - He ate my dog.
如果市长你不去阻止他的话  我们去
If you ain't gonna stop him, mayor, we will.
我不允许镇上存在暴力
I won't have mob violence in this town.
有没有人和他谈谈?
Now, has someone tried talking to him?
-你不能和他讲道理 -他是个恶人
- You can't reason with him. - He's a monster.
我去吧
I'll do it.
我和他谈谈. 看看能不能让他走
I'll talk to him. See if I can get him to go.
那傢伙会把你压扁的
That creature could crush you without trying.
哦   相信我   他会走的
Oh, trust me, he'll have to try.
喂?
Hello?
我叫爱德华.布鲁   我要和你谈谈!
My name is Edward Bloom, and I wanna talk to you!
滚!
Go away!
你不现身我哪都不去!
Now, I'm not going anywhere until you show yourself!
我说   滚啊!
I said, go away!
我已经预知自己是怎么死的...
Armed with the foreknowledge of my own death...
...所以我知道那巨人杀不了我
...I knew the giant couldn't kill me.
不过   希望不要把我的骨头拧断
All the same, I preferred to keep my bones unbroken.
你怎么在这?
Why are you here?
你可以吃我了
So you can eat me.
这个镇决定献上个人祭  那人就是我
The town decided to send a human sacrifice and I volunteered.
我的手臂筋比较多   不过我大腿上的肉还是蛮好吃的
My arms are a little stringy, but there's some good eating in my legs.
我的意思是   我自己都想吃
I mean, I'd be tempted to eat them myself.
我猜....
So I guess, well...
你动作快点的话我就不会疼   真的
If you'd just get it over with quick, because I'm not much for pain, really.
哦   来吧! 我不能回去了! 我是个人祭!
Oh, come on! I can't go back! I'm a human sacrifice!
如果我回去了   他们一定认为我是懦夫
If I go back, they'll think I'm a coward.
我情愿做晚餐也不做懦夫
I'd rather be dinner than a coward.
这里
Here.
你可以从我的手开始. 那很开胃
You can start with my hand. It'll be an appetizer.
我不想吃你 我不想吃任何人
I don't want to eat you. I don't want to eat anybody.
我只是太饿了. 我太高了
I just get so hungry. I'm just too big.
我想过你其实并不高吗...
Did you ever think that maybe you're not too big...
...也许是镇上的人太矮了呢?
...but maybe this town is just too small?
我听说有些城市的建筑很高...
I've heard in real cities there are buildings so tall...
...你还看不到他们的顶部
...you can't even see the tops of them.
-真的? -哦   我不会骗你的
- Really? - Oh, I wouldn't lie to you.
这是可随便享用的自助餐
And all-you-can-eat buffets.
-你可以吃很多   对吗? -是的
- Now, you can eat a lot, can't you? - I can.
那你为什么在这个小镇上浪费时间?
So why are you wasting your time in a small town?
你是个巨人. 你应该去大城市
You're a big man. You should be in a big city.
你是要让我走   对吗?
You're just trying to get me to leave, aren't you?
-你叫什么   巨人? -卡尔.
- What's your name, giant? - Karl.
我叫爱德华. 说实话....
Well, mine's Edward. And truthfully...
我是想让你走   卡尔. 但是是和你一起走
Well, I do want you to leave, Karl. But I want to leave with you.
我的意思是   你觉得这个镇对你来说太小了吗?
I mean, you think this town is too small for you?
对我的雄心来说也太小了
Well, it's too small for a man of my ambition.
你怎么说? 要不要和我一起走?
So, what do you say? Join me?
好的
Okay.
首先   我们要为去的城市做好准备
Now, first, we gotta get you ready for the city.
爱德华.布鲁   阿斯顿的长子...
Edward Bloom, first son of Ashton...
...怀着沉重的心情为你送行
...it's with a heavy heart that we see you go.
请带上城市钥匙...
But take with you this key to the city...
...你随时都能回来...
...and know that any time you want to come back...
...我们的大门为你敞开
...all our doors are open to you.
当我离开阿斯顿的那个下午   似乎所有人都有忠告
That afternoon as I left Ashton, everyone seemed to have advice.
给你自己找个好姑娘  要快!
Find yourself a nice girl, now!
别失去自尊   爱德华.布鲁!
Watch your pride, Edward Bloom!
但是有个人的忠告我最重视
But there was one person whose counsel I held above all others.
他说湖里的那条大鱼...
She said that the biggest fish in the river...
...从来没有被抓过
...gets that way by never being caught.
-她说了什么? -打我
- What'd she say? - Beats me.
离开阿斯顿有两条路:
There were two roads out of Ashton:
新的已经铺好了路面 旧的没有
A new one which was paved and an older one that wasn't.
大家都不走旧的那条...
People didn't use the old one anymore...
...传说那里闹鬼
...and it had developed a reputation for being haunted.
因为我不想再回阿斯顿了...
Well, since I had no intention of ever returning to Ashton...
... 看来这次是个好机会看看老路有什么
...this seemed as good a time as any to find out what lay down that old one.
-你知道谁走过吗? -那个诗人   诺什.温丝勒走过
- You know anyone who's taken it? - That poet, Norther Winslow, did.
他去了法国巴黎
He was going to Paris, France.
我猜他喜欢那里. 没人再有他的消息了
I guess he liked it. No one ever heard from him again.
我要告诉你. 你选另外条路
I'll tell you what. You go the other way.
我在这抄小路   在那头见
I'll cut through here, and I'll meet you on the far side.
你是想逃走  对吗?
You're just trying to run away, aren't you?
拿着
Here.
为了让你相信  你可以拿着我的包
Just to be sure, you can take my pack.
为什么   你这个狗娘--
Why, you son of a...
那就是说一个有理智的人...
Now, there comes a point when a reasonable man...
...在这时候会放下尊严  承认自己犯了个天大的错误
...will swallow his pride and admit that he's made a terrible mistake.
事实是  我从来就不是个有理智的人
The truth is, I was never a reasonable man.
我想起了才主日学校的事...
And what I recall of Sunday school was that...
...事情越艰难   到最后得到的回报越大
...the more difficult something is, the more rewarding it is in the end.
朋友! 欢迎你!
Friend! Welcome to you!
-你叫什么? -爱德华.布鲁.
- What's your name? - Edward Bloom.
-就像花那样"盛开" ? -对的
- "Bloom" like a flower? - Yes.
哦   这里! 你来啦  来这了 "爱德华.布鲁."
Oh, here! Here you are, right here. "Edward Bloom."
我们还没想到你会来
We weren't expecting you yet.
-你们想我? -还没
- You were expecting me? - Not yet.
你一定没有走捷径.
You must've taken a shortcut.
为什么   我走了. 差点杀了我自己
Why, yes, I did. It almost killed me.
人生会给你这些教训. 事实上   长的路往往比较好走
Life will do that to you. And truthfully, the long way is easier.
-但是这也太长了. -长的多
- But it's longer. - Much longer.
现在你在这 这才是关键
And you're here now, and that's what matters.
这里是哪?
What is this place?
幽灵镇. 阿拉巴马最好的藏身之处!
The town of Spectre. Best-kept secret in Alabama!
这里说你是来自阿斯顿的  对吗?
Now, it says here you're from Ashton, right?
我们在阿斯顿遇见的最后一个人是诺什.温丝勒.
Last person we had from Ashton was Norther Winslow.
那个诗人? 他怎么了?
The poet? Whatever happened to him?
他仍然在这. 我给你弄点喝的. 我把所有事都告诉你
He's still here. Let me buy you a drink. I'll tell you all about it.
该死   我让他告诉你!
Hell, I'll have him tell you!
我要见些人   已经迟到了
I have to meet somebody, and I'm already running late.
孩子   我告诉你. 你来早了
Now, son, I already told you. You're early.
告诉我这是不是你吃过的最好吃的馅饼
Now, tell me if that isn't the best pie you ever ate.
确实是
It truly is.
这里什么都好. 水也很清甜
Well, everything tastes better here. Even the water is sweet.
不是太热  太冷   太潮湿
Never gets too hot, too cold, too humid.
在晚上   清风拂过树林...
At night, the wind goes through the trees where you'd swear...
...你就感觉是大型交响乐团为你演奏
...there was a whole symphony out there playing just for you.
嘿! 珍妮!
Hey! Jenny!
回来这里!
Come back here!
珍妮!
Jenny!
嘿   我要那些
Hey, I need those.
-没有比这镇上更松软的土地了 -就像首诗
- There is no softer ground than town. - That almost rhymes.
他是我们这最傑出的诗人. 来吧
He's our poet laureate. Come on.
我答应在这过个下午   只是想知道...
I agreed to spend the afternoon, if only to understand...
...为什么这里感觉这么陌生
...the mystery of how a place could feel so strange and yet so familiar.
这首诗我已经写了12年
I've been working on this poem for 12 years.
真的吗?
Really?
人们都很期望. 我不想辜负他们
There's a lot of expectation. I don't wanna disappoint my fans.
我可以吗?
May I?
只有三行
It's only three lines long.
这就是你不要把未成品给人看的原因
This is why you should never show a work in progress.
我抓住了!
I got him!
里面有水蛭
There's leeches in there.
-你看见那个女人了吗? -她看起来怎么样?
- Did you see that woman? - What did she look like?
-她是.... -裸体的?
- Well, she was... - Was she naked?
是的
Yes, she was.
不是女人.是鱼. 没有人抓住过她
It's not a woman. It's a fish. No one ever catches her.
每个人看到的鱼都不一样
Fish looks different to different people.
我爸爸说它们看上去就像他小时候养的猎犬...
My daddy said it looked like the coon dog he had when he was a kid...
...起死回生
...back from the dead.
哦   该死
Oh, darn.
-你几岁了? -18
- How old are you? - Eighteen.
我8岁. 那就是说在我18岁的时候   你就28了
I'm 8. That means when I'm 18, you'll be 28.
-而我28岁的时候  你也才38. -你的数学不错
- And when I'm 28, you'll only be 38. - You're pretty good at arithmetic.
当我38岁的时候   你48. 没多大区别
And when I'm 38, you'll be 48. That's not much difference at all.
有很大区别   尽管   不是吗?
Sure is a lot now, though, huh?
嘿   爱德华!
Hey, Edward!
玫瑰是红的
紫罗兰是蓝的
我爱幽灵镇....
I love Spectre...
对不起
Excuse me.
珍妮 觉得你人不错 我们都这样认为
Jenny thinks you're quite a catch. We all do.
什么?
What?
我说   你人不错
I said, you're quite a catch.
我要走了
I have to leave.
今晚
Tonight.
为什么?
Why?
对这个镇我不能要求更多了
This town is more than any man could ask for.
如果我要在这停下来   我会觉得我的运气不错
And if I were to end up here, I would consider myself lucky.
但实际上是   我还没准备好在哪停下来
But the truth is, I'm just not ready to end up anywhere.
但是没人离开过这
But no one's ever left.
没鞋你怎么走?
How are you gonna make it without your shoes?
我想会疼. 很疼
Well, I suspect it will hurt. A lot.
对不起   但是.... 再见
Now, I'm sorry, but... Well, goodbye.
-你不会找到更好的地方的. -我也不想
- You won't find a better place. - I don't expect to.
答应我不要回来
Promise me you'll come back.
好的. 将来. 当我真的要回来的时候
I promise. Someday. When I'm really supposed to.
那晚   我有两个结论
That night, I reached two conclusions.
第一个是险路在黑暗中会变得更险
The first was that a dangerous path is made much worse by darkness.
第二个是我绝望而不不可避免地迷了路
The second was that I was hopelessly and irrevocably lost.
这些树林成了我的葬身之处
These woods would become my graveyard.
虽然去往幽灵镇的路困难重重
As difficult as it was to reach Spectre,
我还是注定最终到达了那里
I was fated to get there eventually.
毕竟  没有人可以逃避走到人生的尽头
After all, no man can avoid reaching the end of his life.
这时我认识到  这不是我的人生的尽头
And then I realized this wasn't the end of my life.
我不是这么死的
This isn't how I die.
朋友
Friend.
-你的鞋怎么了? -他们走在我的前头了
- What happened to your shoes? - They kind of got ahead of me.
我不知道你看见了没   但是傑瑟芬有照片...
I don't know if you saw it, but Josephine had some photos...
...就在最近的新闻周刊上
...in the most recent Newsweek.
真的吗?
Really?
太棒了
That's just wonderful.
我花了一周时间在摩洛哥拍那篇报道. 太不可思议了
I spent a week in Morocco for the story. It was incredible.
哦.我们要出个拷贝
Oh. We'll have to pick up a copy.
我不知道你有没有意识到   傑瑟芬...
I don't know if you're aware of this, Josephine...
...但是非洲鹦鹉
...but African parrots,
在它们的老家刚果   他们只会说法语
in their native Congo, they speak only French.
真的吗?
Really?
能让他们说几句英语你就很走运了
You're lucky to get four words out of them in English.
但是如果你穿过森林...
But if you were to walk through the jungle...
...你会听到它们说最棒的法语
...you'd hear them speaking the most elaborate French.
那些鹦鹉什么都谈. 政治  电影  时装
Those parrots talk about everything. Politics, movies, fashion.
任何事情  除了宗教
Everything but religion.
为什么不说宗教   爸爸?
Why not religion, Dad?
说宗教太粗鲁了. 你不会知道你会冒犯什么的
It's rude to talk about religion. You never know who you're gonna offend.
傑瑟芬实际上去年去了刚果
Josephine actually went to the Congo last year.
哦   所以你知道
Oh, so you know.
你好
Hello.
嗨.你怎么样?
Hi. How are you feeling?
哦   我在作梦
Oh, I was dreaming.
梦见什么了?
What were you dreaming about?
哦   我通常不太记得...
Oh, I don't usually remember...
...除非很有预兆. 你知道这些梦是什么意思吗?
...unless they're especially portentous. Do you know what that word means?
意思就是你梦见了可能发生的事
It means when you dream about something that's gonna happen.
就像那晚   我做了个梦...
Like one night, I had a dream...
...一只乌鸦飞过来说:
...where this crow came and said:
"你的阿姨会死"
"Your aunt is gonna die."
我很惊慌   叫醒了父母...
I was so scared, I woke up my parents...
...但是他们说只是个梦就又都睡了
...but they said it was just a dream and to get back to bed.
但是隔天早上   我的史坦斯阿姨就死了
But the next morning, my Aunt Stacy was dead.
太可怕了
That's terrible.
对她来说太可怕了
Terrible for her,
但是想想我   一个孩子有这种力量
but think about me, young boy with that kind of power.
不到三周  那只乌鸦又到了我的梦中...
Wasn't three weeks later when the crow came back to me in a dream...
...说   "你爸爸会死"
...and said, "Your daddy's gonna die."
我不知道该怎么办
I didn't know what to do.
最后我告诉了我父亲   但他说:
I finally told my father, but he said:
"哦   不要担心." 但是我看的出他很慌张
"Oh, not to worry." But I could see he was rattled.
第二天   他变了个人
The next morning, he wasn't himself.
到处看   像是在等什么东西砸他脑袋
Kept looking around, waiting for something to drop on his head.
因为乌鸦没说会怎么样   只是说:
Because the crow didn't say how it was gonna happen, just those words:
"你爸爸会死"
"Your daddy's gonna die."
他很早出去  去了很久
Well, he left home early and was gone a long time.
当他回来的时候   他看上去脸色很吓人...
When he finally came back, he looked terrible...
...就像等了一天斧子掉下来
...like he was waiting for the ax to fall all day.
他跟妈妈说:
He said to my mother:
"这是我一生中最糟的一天"
"I've just had the worst day of my life."
"你觉得这是你一生中最糟的一天?" 她说
"You think you've had a bad day?" she said.
"这个早上   送牛奶的在台阶上死了"
"This morning, the milkman dropped dead on the porch."
因为我母亲和他偷情
Because, see, my mother was banging the milkman.
-我能给你拍张照吗? -哦   你不需要照片
- Can I take your picture? - Oh, you don't need a picture.
查一下 "英俊"这个词
Just look up the word "handsome" in the dictionary.
请?
Please?
好的
All right.
我在婚礼的照片上看到你
I have photos of the wedding to show you.
你和我父亲在一起很不错
There is a great one of you and my father.
我想看看你婚礼的照片 我没看过
I want to see pictures of your wedding. I've never seen any.
因为我们没举办过真正的婚礼
That's because we didn't have a proper wedding.
你的婆婆本不应嫁给我
Your mother-in-law was never supposed to marry me.
-她已经和别人订了婚. -我不知道
- She was engaged to somebody else. - I never knew.
威尔没有告诉你?
Will never told you?
可能这样也好
Probably just as well.
说不定他会讲错话
He would have told it wrong, anyway.
实际上   没有一点添油加醋
All the facts, none of the flavor.
哦. 这就是那个传说
Oh. So this is a tall tale.
故事并不短
Well, it's not a short one.
我刚刚离开幽灵镇去寻找我的使命
I'd just left Spectre and was on my way to discover my destiny.
我不太清楚那是什么...
Not knowing what that would be exactly...
...我寻找每个机会
...I explored every opportunity that presented itself.
可可! 可可! 他们在那
Coco! Coco! There they are.
女士们先生们!
Ladies and gentlemen!
你也许会想你看见了什么非同寻常的东西
You may think you've seen the unusual.
你也许认为自己看到了荒诞的东西
You may think you've seen the bizarre.
但是我找遍了世界的任何角落...
But I've traveled to the five corners of the world...
...让你知道   我从没有看见过这种东西!
...and let me tell you, I've never seen anything like this!
当我遇见那个男人的时候...
When I met this man...
...他正在弗罗里达州摘桔子
...he was picking oranges in Florida.
他的同事叫他佩努. "影子"
His fellow workers called him El Penumbra. "The Shadow."
因为当你在他旁边干活时...
Because when you worked beside him...
...他把日光都挡住了!
...he blocked out the daylight!
不是吓你  夫人   但是如果那个人想要的话...
Not to alarm you, ma'am, but if this man wanted to...
...他可以用脚趾把你的脑袋夹扁...
...he could crush your head between his toes...
...就像捏一个小钱包. 不过他不会这么做的
...like a tiny walnut. But he won't do it.
不. 不   女士们先生们...
No. No, ladies and gentlemen...
...他不会伤害她...
...he will not hurt her...
...因为他是我们的巨人
...because he is our own gentle giant.
女士们先生们   我给你们带来了巨人!
Ladies and gentlemen, I give you Colossus!
女士们先生们   姑娘小伙子们...
Ladies and gentlemen, boys and girls...
...谢谢你们的到来
...thank y'all for coming.
安全回家   各位. 谢谢你们的到来
Drive home safely, everyone. Thank you for coming.
在这个晚上卡尔找到了他的使命
It was on that night Karl met his destiny.
我也差点找到了我的
And I met mine, almost.
他们说当你碰到所爱的人的时候   时间停止了
They say when you meet the love of your life, time stops.
那是真的
And that's true.
当时间开始的时候没人告诉你...
What they don't tell you is that once time starts again...
...它会走得快点来弥补损失的时间
...it moves extra fast to catch up.
你叫什么?
What's your name?
-卡尔. -卡尔
- It's Karl. - Karl.
告诉我   卡尔   你听到过"强制劳役"这个专用名词吗?
Tell me, Karl, have you ever heard the term "involuntary servitude"?
-没有 -"不公平合同"呢?
- No. - "Unconscionable contract"?
-没有 -好
- Nope. - Great.
去那
Here you go.
Here you are.
大屁股先生   到这来...
Mr. Soggybottom, come down this here...
...他可以借用一下你的背来签名
...so he can use your back to sign on it.
好的. 谢谢. 好了
Okay. Thank you. Yeah.
嘿   孩子
Hey, kid.
-你的朋友刚刚让自己变成了明星 -哦   太好了
- Your friend just made himself a star. - Oh, that's great.
-我的律师   大屁股先生. -很高兴见到你
- My attorney, Mr. Soggybottom. - Good to meet you.
很高兴见到你
Pleased to meet you.
怎么了? 我从没有看到客户如此沮丧...
What's the matter? I haven't seen a customer so depressed...
...自从上次大象坐扁了那个农夫的妻子后
...since the elephant sat on that farmer's wife.
"沮丧"?
"Depressed"?
瞧? 那个大傢伙喜欢这个
See? The big guy likes it.
我看见了我结婚的对象
I just saw the woman I'm gonna marry.
我知道了. 但是我失去了她
I know it. But I lost her.
哦   真太糟了
Oh, tough break.
大多数的男人只有在结婚以后才会失去妻子
Well, most men have to get married before they lose their wives.
然而我要花一生去找她. 否则就一个人死去
I'm gonna spend the rest of my life looking for her. That or die alone.
见鬼  孩子
Damn, kid.
让我猜猜. 真的很漂亮?
Let me guess. Real pretty?
微红的金发?
Reddish-blondish hair?
蓝色的衣服?
Blue dress?
对!
Yeah!
我认识她的叔叔.家族的朋友
I know her uncle. Friends of the family.
她是谁? 住哪?
Who is she? Where does she live?
算了.你别浪费时间了. 她和你不一样
Forget it. Don't waste your time. She's out of your league.
-什么? 你还不瞭解我. -我当然瞭解你
- What? You don't even know me. - Sure I do.
你在乡下地方很有名
You were hot shit back in Hickville,
但是这里是现实世界   你要屈尊
but here in the real world, you got squat.
你没有计划和工作
You don't have a plan or a job.
除了背后的衣服什么都没有
Nothing except the clothes on your back.
我身后有一包衣服
Well, I have a whole backpack full of clothes.
哦   谁偷了我的包
Oh, someone stole my backpack.
你在小池塘里是条大鱼   可这里是海洋...
You were a big fish in a small pond, but this here is the ocean...
...你会被淹没的. 回水坑镇去吧
...and you're drowning. Go back to Puddleville.
-你会在那开心的. -你刚才说我没有计划. 我有
- You'll be happy there. - You say I don't have a plan. I do.
我要找个姑娘   娶回来   和她共渡余生
I'll find that girl, marry her, and spend the rest of my life with her.
我没有工作   如果你给我一个不就有了
I don't have a job, but I would have a job if you gave me one.
我没有很多钱...
And I may not have much...
...但是我比你会遇见的任何男人都更有决心
...but I have more determination than any man you're likely to meet.
对不起   孩子.我不做慈善事业的 来吧   大个子
I'm sorry, kid. I don't do charity. Come on, big boy.
等等. 看   我会为你昼夜工作的...
Wait. Look, I'll work night and day for you...
...你不用付我钱
...and you won't have to pay me.
你只要告诉我她是谁
You just have to tell me who she is.
每个月你为我工作...
Every month you work for me...
...我就告诉你一件关於她的事. 这是我的最后开价
...l'll tell you one thing about her. That's my final offer.
让我们开始
Let's get started.
从那刻起   我做所有卡洛维先生吩咐的事
From that moment on, I did everything Mr. Calloway asked.
我连续工作三天没有停下来吃过东西
I'd go three days without stopping to eat.
四天没有睡觉
And four days without sleeping.
让我前进的动力就是见到那个姑娘...
What kept me going was the promise of meeting the girl...
... 那个我要娶的姑娘
...who would be my wife.
连在一起   就那样
Stick together, that's the way it's gonna be.
-就是那样   以后就保持那样 -卡洛维先生?
- The way it was, and the way it will be. - Mr. Calloway, sir?
已经一个月了
It's been a month today.
这个姑娘   你今生的爱...
This girl, the love of your life...
...她最喜欢水仙
...her favorite flowers are daffodils.
-拿着.... -水仙
- So get that stuff... - Daffodils.
水仙
Daffodils.
遵守他的诺言...
True to his word...
...每个月阿莫斯都会告诉我一点那个...
...every month Amos would tell me something new...
...我梦中的姑娘的事
...about the woman of my dreams.
玩的开心   玩的开心
Enjoy yourselves, enjoy yourselves.
她要上大学了
She's going to college.
大学. 她要上大学了
College. She's going to college.
她喜欢音乐
She likes music.
音乐. 她喜欢音乐
Music. She likes music.
几个月后   对於这个我要娶的姑娘我了解了很多...
Over the months, I learned a lot about the woman I would marry...
...但是不是她的名字   也不知道去哪找她
...but not her name, and not where to find her.
终於到了.我不能再等了
That time had come. I couldn't wait any longer.
卡洛维先生?
Mr. Calloway?
是爱德华.布鲁. 我要和你谈谈
It's Edward Bloom. I need to talk to you.
卡洛维先生?
Mr. Calloway?
不. 等等!
No. Wait!
那天晚上   我发现你认为邪恶的东西...
That night, I discovered that most things you consider evil or wicked...
...只是出於孤独或者是缺乏社交上的分寸
...are simply lonely and lacking in social niceties.
我没杀死什么东西   是吗?
Didn't kill anything, did I?
几只兔子而已. 不过我认为其中一只本来就是死的
A few rabbits. But I think one of them was already dead.
怪不得我有点消化不良
That would explain the indigestion.
谢谢
Thank you.
我看错你了   孩子
I was wrong about you, kid.
你也许什么长处   但是其实你有的   而且很多
You may not have much, but what you got, you got a lot of.
你能追到那姑娘
You could get any girl.
我只想要一个
There's only one I want.
她...
Her name...
...叫桑德拉.坦浦顿
...is Sandra Templeton.
去了奥本念书
She goes to Auburn.
学期快结束了   所以你最好快点
Semester's almost over, so you better hurry.
谢谢你  谢谢你
Thank you. Thank you.
-祝你好运   孩子! -谢谢你   先生!
- Good luck, kid! - Thank you, sir!
-再见 -再见   爱德华.
- Bye, now. - Bye, Edward.
说完再见   我换了三趟火车...
After saying my goodbyes, I hopped three trains...
...在下午到了奥本大学
...to get to Auburn that afternoon.
你不认识我   我叫爱德华.布鲁...
You don't know me, but my name is Edward Bloom...
...我爱你
...and I love you.
我做了三年工就是为了知道你是谁
I've spent the last three years working to find out who you are.
有几次我被枪打中  被刀刺伤
I've been shot, stabbed, and trampled a
还被踩过   我的肋骨断了两次
few times. I broke my ribs twice.
但是能够见到你我认为一切都是值得的...
But it's all been worth it to see you here now...
...最后能和你说话
...and to finally get to talk to you.
因为我要娶你
Because I'm destined to marry you.
从我在马戏团见到你的第一刻起我就知道
I knew it when I saw you at the circus, and I know it now more than ever.
-对不起 -你不必道歉
- I'm sorry. - You don't have to apologize to me.
我是你今天所看见的最幸运的人
I'm the luckiest person you'll find today.
不   对不起我不想结婚
No, I'm sorry I'm engaged to be married.
但是你错了.我真的瞭解你
But you're wrong. I do know you.
至少听过你的名声
At least by reputation.
从阿斯顿来的爱德华.布鲁
Edward Bloom from Ashton.
瞧   实际上我已经和从阿斯顿来的丹.普来斯定婚了
See, I'm actually engaged to a boy from Ashton. Don Price.
他比你大一点
He was a few years older than you.
那么....
Well...
恭喜你了
Congratulations.
打扰你很抱歉
I'm sorry to have bothered you.
停! 并不有趣
Stop it! It's not funny.
可怜的孩子
That poor boy.
命运总是残酷地捉弄着你
Fate has a cruel way of circling around on you.
好不容易离开了阿斯顿...
After all this work to leave Ashton...
...我爱的姑娘却和那来的人定了婚
...the girl I love was now engaged to one of its biggest jerks.
是男人斗争的时候了...
There's a time when a man needs to fight...
...他需要接受使命落空的情况...
...and a time when he needs to accept that his destiny's lost...
... 船起航了   傻瓜才会向前
...the ship has sailed, and that only a fool will continue.
事实上   我一直是个傻瓜
Truth is, I've always been a fool.
桑德拉.坦浦顿   我爱你   我要娶你!
Sandra Templeton, I love you, and I will marry you!
就像你看到的   如果这些规则适用我们的生活...
So as you can see, if we apply these rules to our everyday life...
...供求更有意义
...supply and demand makes much more sense.
看下一张图  引入这一点将会更有说服力--
Take a look at the next graph, and the import of this will be even stronger...
--三个小时
- for three hours.
看!
Look!
-水仙! -这是你最喜欢的花
- Daffodils! - They're your favorite flower.
你哪里去弄来这么多?
How did you get so many?
我5个州都打了电话
I called everywhere in five states.
我告诉他们这是我娶妻的唯一方法
I told them it was the only way to get my wife to marry me.
你似乎不瞭解我
You don't even know me.
我用余生去瞭解
I have the rest of my life to find out.
桑德拉!
Sandra!
是丹. 答应我别伤害他
It's Don. Promise you won't hurt him.
如果这是你想要的  我发誓
If that's what you want, I swear to it.
-布鲁? -丹
- Bloom? - Don.
你到底在干什么? 她是我的女孩. 我的!
What the hell are you doing? This is my girl. Mine!
我没注意到她已经名花有主了
I wasn't aware that she belonged to anyone.
出什么事了? 难道你害怕得不敢还击了?
What's the matter? Are you too scared to fight back?
我发誓我不会
I promised I wouldn't.
停下来!
Stop it!
丹   停!
Don, stop!
虽然我被揍的很惨   但是最后输的却是丹.普来斯
While I took the beating of a lifetime, Don Price was ultimately defeated.
用力过猛使得他天生的心脏瓣膜缺陷恶化
All the physical activity had worsened a congenital valve defect.
简单来说   他的心脏还不够强壮
Put simply, his heart wasn't strong enough.
丹! 我不会嫁给你的
Don! I will never marry you.
什么? 你是说   你爱这个傢伙?
What? You mean, you love this guy?
他还是个陌生人   但我喜欢他胜过你
He's almost a stranger, and I prefer him to you.
最后   桑德拉仍然在同一天去了教堂
As it turned out, Sandra was able to keep her same date at the chapel.
只是新郎换了人
Only the groom had changed.
我记得你说过你没有在教堂举行过婚礼
I thought you said you didn't have a church wedding.
我们都好了  但是还有点麻烦
We were all set to, but there was a complication.
这药会让你口渴吗?
Is it the medicine that's making you thirsty?
实际上   这一直很口渴
Truth is, I've been thirsty my whole life.
不知道为什么
Never really known why.
在我11岁的时候....
There was a time when I was 11...
你在谈你的婚礼
You were talking about your wedding.
我没有忘记.我绕着弯在讲话
I didn't forget. I was just working on a tangent.
你也知道   大多数人说话都很直接
You see, most men, they'll tell you a story straight through.
这样并不複杂  但是也很没趣
It won't be complicated, but it won't be interesting, either.
我喜欢你的故事
I like your stories.
我喜欢你
And I like you.
在你在马戏团工作的时候   你没有一个固定的地址
Well, when you work for the circus, you don't have a regular address.
三年后  有很多信我没收到
So after three years, there was a lot of undelivered mail.
在我住院的四周时间里...
During the four weeks I was in the hospital...
...邮差终於找到了我
...the postmaster finally caught up with me.
尽管我的心也许是属於桑德拉的...
And it seems that while my heart belonged to Sandra...
...我身体的其它部分则属於美国政府
...the rest of my body belonged to the U.S. government.
当时在军中服役期最长可达三年...
A hitch in the Army was up to three years at that point...
...而我已经等了三年才见到桑德拉...
...and having waited three years just to meet Sandra...
...我知道我没有办法离开她这么久时间
...I knew I couldn't survive being away from her that long.
所以我就接那种危险的任务...
So I took every hazardous assignment I could find...
...希望能把我的时间缩短一年也好
...with the hope of getting my time down to less than a year.
上! 上!
Go! Go!
当我接到个秘密行动...
When I was offered a secret mission...
...要我偷王开堂发电厂的图纸...
...to steal the plans for the Wong Kai Tang power plant...
...我跳了下去报效祖国
...I jumped at the chance to serve my country.
上! 上!
Go! Go!
嘿 兄弟 兄弟 什么乱七八糟的 下台吧
这傢伙谁找的 真他妈要枪毙
有很漂亮的小姐为我们演出
女孩有时会感觉孤独
没有爱人来爱她
有时候孤独难耐
她内心要爆发
见到一个男人就抓紧 扯去他的衣衫
可她不会.她不能
她需要一个特殊 非凡 超群的男人
因为那与我一般容貌的女孩
她想要得到 可她有需要
谁有需要?
Any of you got needs?
我有过双重的冒险
我流过双倍的泪
我在一半的岁月中有过双倍的不幸
现在我需要一个男人
能有着加倍的意志
我需要这样的男人
因为宝贝  我有双倍的爱要付出
因为宝贝 我有双倍的爱要付出
你怎么每次都错过暗示?
How could you miss your cue?
你让我在那一个人看上去像个傻瓜
You make me look like a fool out there alone.
你不是一个人!
You weren't alone!
你到底是谁?
Who the hell are you?
我不会伤害你的
I'm not going to hurt you.
你当然不敢
Damn right you're not.
守卫!
GUARD!
不要打扰我们!
Tell your men not to bother us!
把门帘关上!
And close that curtain!
我要你帮忙
Please, I need your help.
你怎么知道我们能帮你?
What makes you think we'll help you?
接下来一小时   我要向桑德拉.坦普顿表白...
Over the next hour, I described my love for Sandra K. Templeton...
...是我经历的苦难让我出现在她们面前
...and the ordeal that brought me before them.
就像以往一样  这份爱拯救了我
As it had always been, this love was my salvation.
这是命中注定的
It was destined to be.
我们制定了一个周密的逃跑计划...
We put together an elaborate plan for escape...
...包括乘捕鲸船去俄国...
...involving a whaling ship to Russia...
...然后乘游艇去古巴   再坐一艘又小又髒的独木舟到达迈阿密
...a barge to Cuba, and a small, dirty canoe to Miami.
我们都知道这很危险
We all knew it would be dangerous.
我们去了美国可以做点什么呢?
And what are we supposed to do when we get to America?
我会帮你们安排的
I can get you bookings.
我认识娱乐圈的大人物
I know the biggest man in show business.
鲍勃?!
Bob Hope?!
比他大牌
Bigger.
准备好了吗?
Ready?
我和双胞胎开始了我们的坚信旅程...
And so the twins and I began our arduous journey...
...绕了半个地球
...halfway around the world.
不幸的是   没有办法可以发消息回美国
Unfortunately, there was no way to send a message back to America.
不出所料军方以为我战死沙场了
And so it was no surprise that the Army believed I was dead.
不   天哪!
No, God!
四个月后   桑德拉一直做着恶梦
After four months, Sandra had gotten over the worst of the nightmares.
当电话铃响的时候   她不知道打电话来的是我
When the phone rang, she didn't think it was somehow me calling her.
当车开过的时候   她没有起身开窗看
When a car drove past, she didn't get up to check out the window.
我和你父亲昨天在谈
I talked with your father last night.
你从没有告诉我你父母是如何相遇的
You never told me how your parents met.
他们是在奥本大学认识的
They met at Auburn.
细节怎么样呢? 他们怎么坠入爱河的?
What about the details? How they fell in love.
马戏团. 战争
The circus. The war.
这些你从来没告诉过我
You never told me any of that.
因为大多数的事没发生过
That's because most of it never happened.
但是很浪漫
But it's romantic.
-什么? -什么   比起和一个法国女人争吵浪漫...
- What? - What, I know better...
...我知道的更多
...than to argue romance with a French woman.
你爱你的父亲吗?
Do you love your father?
每个人都爱自己的父亲 他很招人喜欢
Everyone loves my father. He's a very likable guy.
你爱他吗?
Do you love him?
你必须理解
You have to understand.
当我长大的时候   他出去的时间比在家时间多
When I was growing up, he was gone more than he was there.
我就开始想他是不是在其他地方过着另外的生活
And I started thinking maybe he's got this second life somewhere else.
另外的家庭   另外的房子
Another family, another house.
他离开我们去他们那
And he leaves us and goes to them.
或者   或者....
Or, or...
或者没有第二个家庭. 可能他不想要个家
Or maybe there is no second family. Maybe he never wanted a family.
不管怎么样   他喜欢他另外的生活和讲故事...
Whatever it is, he likes his second life better and he tells his stories...
...因为他不甘忍受这个无聊的地方
...because he can't stand this boring place.
-但那不是真的. -那么   什么是真的?
- But it's not true. - Well, what's true?
他从来没有说过真话
He's never told me a single true thing.
看   嘿....
Look, hey...
我知道你为什么喜欢他了
I know why you like him.
我知道为什么每个人都喜欢他
I know why everyone likes him.
但是我要告诉你  我没有疯
But I need you to tell me that I'm not crazy.
哦  你没有
Oh, you're not.
我想你应该和他谈谈
And I think you should talk to him.
拉里.普凯特的雪佛莱让客人这么说
Larry Puckett's Chevrolet lets the customer do the talking.
拉里.普凯特的通用车在车厂做担保
Larry Puckett's GM-certified vehicles are under factory warranty.
你可以最多比生产者建议零售价少付40%
And you can save up to 40 percent off the original MSRP.
-我有跟你讲过--? -有
- Did I ever tell you about...? - Yes.
枫树和别克的故事? 我们听过
The maple tree and the Buick? We've heard it.
我知道有人没听过
I know someone who hasn't.
-那-- -树倒在车上  把糖浆洒了一地
- The... - Tree fell on the car, spilling the syrup.
引来了很多苍蝇  沾在车上...
Which attracted the flies, which got stuck to it...
...飞走时带上整个车
...and flew off with the whole car.
但是真实的故事是我怎么开走这车
But the real story is how I got the car.
-你知道的-- -父亲?
- You see... - Dad?
儿子
Son.
能谈谈吗?
Can we talk?
我想我该去洗盘子了
I think I'll get started on these dishes.
我来帮你
I'll help you.
-你知道冰山吗  爸爸? -我?
- You know about icebergs, Dad? - Do I?
我看过一次
I saw an iceberg once.
他们当时正把它拉到德克萨斯州当饮用水
They were hauling it down to Texas for drinking water.
可他们没想到里面还冻了一头大象
They didn't count on there being an elephant frozen inside.
-长毛的那种.毛象 -爸爸!
- The woolly kind. A mammoth. - Dad!
什么?
What?
我只是打个比方
I'm trying to make a metaphor here.
你不应该用提问的方式开始...
Well, you shouldn't have started with a question...
...因为人们喜欢回答问题
...because people want to answer questions.
你不能从"关於冰山的是...."开始
You should've started with, "The thing about icebergs is..."
好  好. 关於冰山的问题是你只看了10%
Okay, okay. The thing about icebergs is you only see 10 percent.
在水下的90%你没看见
The other 90 percent is below the water where you can't see it.
那是...
And that's...
...那是和你有关的   爸爸
...what it is with you, Dad.
我只看出了一点...
I am only seeing this little bit...
...就是在水面上的
...that sticks above the water.
哦   你只看见我鼻子下的? 我的下巴?我的--
Oh, you're only seeing down to my nose? My chin? My...
爸爸   我不知道你是...
Dad, I have no idea who you are...
...因为你没告诉过我什么真相
...because you've never told me a single fact.
我告诉了你几千个真相
I've told you a thousand facts,
威尔. 这就是我干的  讲故事!
Will. That's what I do, I tell stories!
你说...谎   爸爸
You tell... lies, Dad.
你总是说那些有趣的谎言
You tell amusing lies.
这些就是你在一个5岁孩子临睡前讲的
Stories are what you tell a 5-year-old at bedtime.
当你的儿子长到10  15  20  30岁时...
They're not elaborate mythologies that you maintain...
...你就不能再编织那些动人的神话了
...when your son is 10 and 15 and 20 and 30.
我相信你
And I believed you.
我早就不应该相信你的故事了  但我信了很久
I believed your stories so much longer than I should have.
当我意识到你说的是不可能的...
Then when I realized everything you said was impossible...
...我感觉自己想个傻瓜一样相信你
...I felt like a fool to have trusted you.
你就像圣诞老人和复活节兔子
You're like Santa Claus and the Easter Bunny.
很动人  但也很虚假
Just as charming and just as fake.
你认为我虚假
You think I'm fake.
只是在表面上  爸爸 但都是我看见的
Only on the surface, Dad. But it's all I've ever seen.
看着
Look.
我要走了...
I'm about to have...
...我有自己的孩子了
...a kid of my own.
如果你在一生都没能理解我...
It would kill me if he went through his whole life...
...我会很难过
...never understanding me.
你会难过   恩?
It would kill you, huh?
你要什么   威尔? 你想成为谁?
What do you want, Will? Who do you want me to be?
你
Just yourself.
好   坏   让我看看真实的你
Good, bad, everything. Just show me who you are for once.
自出生以来我一直是我
I've been nothing but myself since the day I was born.
如果你看不见   是你的失败   不是我的!
And if you can't see that, it's your failing, not mine!
你父亲决定自己要间办公室...
Your father decided that he needed to have an office...
...当然   在家是不行的
...and, of course, it wouldn't do to have it in the house.
那么....
So...
你应该比我更瞭解什么是重点
You'll know better than me what's important.
是什么?
What is it?
在战争期间
It was during the war.
你父亲失踪了 他们以为他已经牺牲
Your father went missing. They thought he was dead.
哦   真的是这样吗?
Oh, that really happened?
你父亲说的不完全是编造的
Not everything your father says is a complete fabrication.
我想我要去看看他
I think I'll go check on him.
我要躺会
I need to lie down for a bit.
好   去吧
Okay, go.
战争以后  阿拉巴马的孩子们回到家园找工作
After the war, the sons of Alabama returned home, looking for work.
每个人都比我有优势
Each had the advantage over me.
他们或者   而我已经被官方证实死亡
They were alive, while I was officially deceased.
前途渺茫...
With my prospects few...
...我找了一份适合自己的旅游推销工作
...I took a job as a traveling salesman. It suited me.
你可以说爱德华 布鲁...
If there was one thing you can say about Edward Bloom...
...是个社交人物
...it's that I am a social person.
-恭喜 -谢谢   险胜
- Congratulations. - Thank you, sir.
我每次都要出去几周
I could be gone for weeks at a time.
但是每个星期五   我把钱都...
But every other Friday, I put all the money I made...
...存入一个帐号...
...into an account set aside for a proper house...
...用来买白色栅栏的房子
...with a white picket fence.
我想借此机会向大家介绍我们的新产品...
I'd like a moment of your time to tell you about my new product...
...自动手
...the Handi-matic.
几年后   我在其他城市做不同的商品...
A few years later, I added other products and other cities...
...直到我的领地从沿海地区延伸到西部的德州
...until my territory stretched from the coast to western Texas.
爱德华?
Edward?
爱德华 布鲁!
Edward Bloom!
是我   诺什.温斯勒
It's me, Norther Winslow.
我不相信
I don't believe it.
我很惊讶竟然远在德州...
I was astonished to see the greatest poet of both Ashton and Spectre...
...看到了阿斯顿和幽灵镇两地最伟大的诗人
...all the way out in Texas.
我想你知道   当你离开幽灵镇的时候  我的眼界开阔了
I want you to know, when you left Spectre, it opened my eyes.
外面的生活我还没有体验过呢
There was a whole life out there that I was not living.
所以我也出来了
So I traveled.
我去了法国  非洲  半个南美
I saw France, Africa, half of South America.
每天都有新的经历. 这是我的格言
Every day, a new adventure. That's my motto.
太好了   诺什. 我为你感到高兴
That's great, Norther. I'm happy for you.
你现在在干什么?
What are you doing now?
我要抢劫这个地方
I'm robbing this place.
好了  所有人蹲下!
All right, everybody down!
嘿! 把枪滑过来
Hey! Just slide that over.
-你能不能把它拿过来? -什么?
- Would you mind grabbing that? - What?
枪
The gun.
我会拿光现金抽屉里的钱...
I'm gonna be cleaning out the cash drawers...
...而我的助手会去金库
...and my associate here is gonna handle the vault.
好了   你! 你当我的助手   好吗?
All right, you! You help my friend, okay?
我们走!
Let's go!
对不起   女士 是我
I'm sorry, ma'am. I am.
我真的不想任何人受伤
I really just don't want anyone to get hurt.
不是的
It's not that.
只是....
It's just...
没钱
There's no money.
我们完全破产了. 不要告诉任何人
We're completely bankrupt. Don't tell anybody.
结果储蓄和贷款的钱早已被洗劫一空...
It turned out that the Savings & Loan had already been robbed...
...不是被持枪的强盗  而是被德州的地产投机商抢走的
...not by armed bandits, but by speculators in Texas real estate.
好了   我们走!
All right, let's go!
诺什!
Norther!
对! 这里有$400!
Yeah! There's gotta be close to $400 here!
这还只是抽屉里的
And that's just from the drawers.
我们来看看你从金库里拿了多少
Let's see what you got from the vault.
这点吗? 整个金库里?
This is it? The whole vault?
恐怕是的
I'm afraid so.
有你的存款单
It's got your deposit slip on it.
我只是不想让你空手而归
Well, I just didn't want you leaving empty-handed.
有些事情你应该知道. 他们没钱的理由....
There's something you should know. The reason they don't have money...
我告诉诺什德州石油价格难以预计的变化...
I told Norther about the vagaries of Texas oil money...
...还有房地产价格效应...
...and its effect on real-estate prices...
...以及信託程序的不严格执行...
...and how lax enforcement of fiduciary process...
...已经使得储蓄和贷款减少
...had made savings and loans particularly vulnerable.
听到了这个  诺什留下了个结论:
Hearing this news, Norther was left with one conclusion:
我应该去华尔街. 钱都在那里
I should go to Wall Street. That's where all the money is.
我知道我犯罪的日子已经结束了...
I knew then that while my days as a criminal were over...
谢谢你的帮忙!
Thanks for the hand!
...诺什开始了
...Norther's were just beginning.
当诺什赚到了他的第一个100万时...
When Norther made his first million dollars...
...他给了我10  000的支票
...he sent me a check for 10,000.
我拒绝了   但他说这是他付给我的职业咨询费
I protested, but he said it was my fee as his career advisor.
这些钱足以给我的妻子买一栋有白色...
It was enough to buy my wife a proper house...
... 栅栏的房子
...with a white picket fence.
那就是男人对财富的最大梦想
And for that, it was all the riches a man could ever want.
我乾透了
I was drying out.
我知道
I see.
我看我们该给你买个洒水器...
I think we ought to get you a plant mister...
...那样我们就可以像浇花一样给你浇水了
...so we can just spray you like a fern.
来吧
Come, now.
我想我是永远不会干透的
I don't think I'll ever dry out.
你拿着. 我看看....
You carry on. I'll see...
你好
Hello.
-你是珍尼佛.希尔? -我是
- Are you Jennifer Hill? - I am.
你是威尔吧
And you're Will.
我看过你的照片. 所以我认的出你
I've seen a picture of you. That's how I recognize you.
听着   肯尼   我们今天可不可以不要上了?
Listen, Kenny, why don't we skip the lesson today?
下周再上
We can go again next week.
我要把这个换给妈妈吗?
Do I have to give it back to my mom?
你不想说就不要说了
Well, I won't tell her if you won't.
你怎么认识我父亲的?
How did you know my father?
这是他去推销的必经之地...
Well, this was on his sales route...
...他经常经过这里  每个人都认识他
...so he was through here all the time, and everyone in town knew him.
你有事吗?
Were you having an affair?
哇. 哇   你说了
Wow. Wow, you just said it.
我还准备再绕上半小时呢
I was expecting to dance around this for another half-hour.
我见过他和这个女人在一起. 他和她调情. 他一直这样
I've seen him with women. He flirts. He always has.
从某种程度上看   我只是猜测...
And on some level, I just presumed that he was...
...他欺骗了我妈 但是我没有证据
...cheating on my mom. I just never had proof.
我能问个问题吗?
Well, can I ask you a question?
如果你找到了契约   为什么不问艾迪?
If you found this deed, why didn't you just ask Eddie?
因为他快死了
Because he's dying.
看   我不知道你瞭解多少情况
Look, I don't know how much you want to know about any of this.
你对你父亲有印象...
You have one image of your father...
...我不应该改变它...
...and it'd be wrong of me to change it...
...尤其是在游戏的结尾
...especially this late in the game.
我父亲说了他从来没说过的事...
My father talked about things he never did...
...我相信这些他从没有说过
...and I'm sure he did a lot of things that he never talked about.
我试着在两者之间找到共同点
I'm just trying to reconcile the two.
首先你要瞭解...
The first thing you have to understand...
...你父亲没想到会来这
...is that your father never meant to end up here.
然而他来了
Yet he did.
两次
Twice.
第一次   他来早了
The first time, he was early.
第二次   他来晚了
The second time, he was late.
那些日子  你父亲为自己工作
Those days, your father was working for himself.
爱德华.布鲁是这样一个人...
If there's one thing you could say about Edward Bloom...
...他是个喜欢社交的人   大家都喜欢和他说话
...it's that he was a social person, and people took a liking to him.
一天晚上   他出门三周后回来...
One night, he was returning from three weeks on the road...
... 遇上了从没碰到过的暴风雨
...when he hit a thunderstorm unlike any in his life.
命运就是喜欢捉弄人...
Fate has a way of circling back on a man...
...让他大吃一惊
...and taking him by surprise.
一个人在生命的各种时段看事物角度也是不同的
A man sees things differently at different times in his life.
这个镇在年老的他看来已经不同了
This town didn't seem the same now that he was older.
一条新路已经把外面的世界带进了幽灵镇...
A new road had brought the outside world to Spectre...
...随之而来的是  银行  抵押和债务
...and with it, banks, liens and debt.
只要你看的到的地方   就有人破产
Almost everywhere you looked, people were bankrupt.
今天为幽灵镇举行一次拍卖
The auction today is for the town of Spectre.
-开价 $1 0  000. -於是爱德华.布鲁...
- The opening bid will be $ 10,000. - So Edward Bloom...
-...决定买下这个镇 -50  000.
...decided to buy the town. - 50,000.
-我不能相信我的眼睛-- -他从来不是个有钱的人...
- I couldn't believe my eyes... - He was never a wealthy man...
...但是他能让别人变的有钱   现在他找他们帮忙
...but he had made other men rich, and now he asked for their favors.
-我决定存.... -他们中的大多数人没见过幽灵镇
- I'm trying to save... - Most of them hadn't seen Spectre.
只是听爱德华描述过
They only had Edward's words to describe it.
有这些已经够了. 他卖了出去
That's all he needed. He sold them on the dream.
首先他买了农场
So first he bought the farms.
然后是房子. 接着是商店
Then he bought the houses. And then he bought the stores.
他买的地方   里面的人都不用离开或者付房租
Whatever he bought, the people were not asked to leave or pay rent.
他们被要求像平时一样生活
They were just asked to keep doing as they were doing.
那样   他就能保证这个镇不会灭亡
In that way, he could make sure the town would never die.
在6个月里   整个镇都信任了他
Within six months, his trust had purchased the entire town.
所有的人
With one exception.
你一定是爱德华 布鲁
You must be Edward Bloom.
你怎么知道的?
How do you know?
不会有人没事来这里的
No one would come out here unless they had business.
除了你也没人会来找我
And no one would have business with me except for you.
你把镇买下来了
You're buying the town.
显然我注意到了   我要弥补一下
Apparently I overlooked this one piece of it, and I'd like to remedy that.
为了让这个镇保全下来   整个镇子
In order for the town to be preserved, the trust must own it, in its entirety.
我听说了
And so I've heard.
我会高价买下来. 你不必搬
I'll offer you more than it's worth. And you won't have to move.
契约上除了名字什么都不会变
Nothing will change except the name on the deed, you have my word.
我跟你直说吧
Now, let me get this straight.
你从我这里把沼泽买走   但我可以住在里面?
You buy the swamp from me, but I'll stay in it?
你将拥有这房子   可这里还是我住?
You'll own the house, but it'll still be mine?
我住这   你可以自由出入
I'll be here, and you'll come and go as you please to one place or another.
对吗?
Do I have that right?
应该说   是的
In so many words, yes.
对   我不这么想   布鲁先生
Yeah, then I don't think so, Mr. Bloom.
如果能不改变   我宁愿不要改变...
If nothing's gonna change, I'd just as soon it not change...
...这些东西我很久没变了
...in the way things haven't been changing all this time.
你什么也不会失去. 你可以问问镇上的其他人
It's not like you'll lose anything. You can ask anyone in town.
你为什么要买下这   布鲁先生?
Why are you buying this land, Mr. Bloom?
某种中年危机吗?
Some sort of midlife crisis?
你不买债券  买镇子?
Instead of buying a convertible, you buy a town?
助人为乐
Helping people makes me happy.
我不认为你会开心
I'm not convinced you should be happy.
-对不起. 我有没有冒犯你? -没
- I'm sorry. Have I offended you? - No.
你遵守了承诺
You did exactly what you promised.
你回来了. 我还以为会更早点
You came back. I was just expecting you sooner.
你是比曼的女儿
You're Beamen's daughter.
名字变了. 你结婚了吗?
Your name's different. Did you get married?
我18. 他28. 差很多
I was 18. He was 28. Turns out that was a big difference.
我不会把房子卖给你的   布鲁先生
I won't be selling you this house, Mr. Bloom.
我知道
I see.
谢谢你
Well, thank you for your time.
-门卡住了 -是
- It's stuck. - Yeah.
-哦   对不起! 我-- -好了. 别管了
- Oh, I'm so sorry! l... - It's okay. Just leave it.
-不   我-- -请! 走吧
- No, I'll... - Please! Just go.
-但是-- -走吧
- But... - Go.
大多数人在这种情况下会接受失败继续走下去
Most men in that situation would accept their failure and move on.
但是爱德华不在其中
But Edward was not like most men.
停!
Hold!
他们的性格完全不同但是...
They both had completely different characters but...
...只有两条腿
...well, just one pair of legs.
几个月过去了   他找了很多东西修理...
As the months passed, he found more and more things to fix...
...直到那小屋完全变了一个模样
...until the shack no longer resembled itself.
当然   最好的地方是材料换了
Of course, the best part was coming up with the new material.
当我和双胞胎去哈瓦那时...
By the time the twins and I had got to Havana...
...我们想出了一条新路线
...we'd worked out a new routine,
只用一把尤格里里琴和一只口琴
using only a ukulele and a harmonica.
-那么.... -你可以离开那了
- Well... - You could leave it there.
不
No.
不要
Now, don't.
不要尴尬. 我不能让你认为....
Don't be embarrassed. I should never have let you think that...
我爱我的妻子
I'm in love with my wife.
我知道
Yeah, I know.
从我见她的第一天到我死去...
And from the first day I saw her until the day I die...
...她是我的唯一
...she's the only one.
幸运的女孩
Lucky girl.
对不起   珍妮. 我认真的
I'm sorry, Jenny. I am.
等等! 爱德华.
Wait! Edward.
一天   爱德华.布鲁离开了...
One day, Edward Bloom left...
...没有再回到这个他苦心经营的镇上
...and never returned to the town he'd saved.
至於那个女孩...
As for the girl...
...通常的说法是她变成了女巫...
...the common belief was that she'd become a witch...
...并很疯狂於此
...and crazy at that.
她自己成了一个传奇
She became something of a legend herself.
这个故事在开始的时候就结束了
And the story ended where it began.
逻辑上来看   你不能成为女巫   因为她...
Logically, you couldn't be the witch, because she was...
...在他小的时候就很老了
...old when he was young.
你像你父亲那样思考才符合逻辑
Well, it's logical if you think like your father.
对於他来说只有两种女人:
See, to him there's only two women:
你的母亲...
Your mother...
...和其他人
...and everyone else.
一天...
And one day...
...我意识到我爱上了一个不爱我的男人
...I realized I was in love with a man who could never love me back.
我生活在童话世界里
I was living in a fairy tale.
我不知道我该不该告诉你这些
I'm not sure I should've told you any of this.
不   不   不   我想知道. 我....
No, no, no, I wanted to know. I'm...
很高兴能知道
I'm glad I know.
我希望我对你能像他对你这么重要
I wanted to be as important to him as you were.
我....
And I'm...
我永远不可能
I was never gonna be.
我只是虚幻的
I was make-believe.
他另外的生活   你....
And his other life, you...
是真实的
You were real.
妈妈?
Mom?
傑瑟芬?
Josephine?
威尔!
Will!
出什么事了?
What happened?
你父亲中风了
Your father had a stroke.
他和你妈妈在楼上 还有本耐特大夫
He's upstairs with your mom and Dr. Bennett.
他会好吗?
Is he gonna be okay?
我觉得我...
I don't suppose that I could...
...应该留下来. 我的意思是   假如....
...stay here with him. I mean, in case...
假如他醒了   我应该在这里
In case he wakes up, I really ought to be here.
我留下来
I'll stay.
你和傑瑟芬回家吧. 我陪夜
Why don't you go home with Josephine. I'll stay tonight.
-好吗? -好
- Is that okay? - Fine.
威尔  如果有事打电话...?
Will, you'll call if there's any...?
知道. 知道了. 我会打的
I will. I will. I'll call.
-你想和爸爸呆会吗? -是的.谢谢
- Do you want some time with Dad? - Yes. Thank you.
很高兴看见你不是来真心谈话的
Glad to see you're not trying to have a heartfelt talk.
我最烦的一件事就是...
One of my greatest annoyances is when...
...和不想听的人倾诉
...people try to talk to those who can't hear them.
我们有优势
Well, we have an advantage.
我和父亲从来不说话
My father and I never talk.
你父亲告诉过你关於你出生那天的事吗?
Your father ever tell you about the day you were born?
对   1000多次了. 他抓住了那条抓不到的鱼的事
Yeah, a thousand times. He caught an uncatchable fish.
不是那个. 真实的故事. 他和你说了吗?
Not that. The real story. He ever tell you that?
没有
No.
你母亲下午3点进来
Well, your mother came in about 3 in the afternoon.
她的邻居送她进来的   考虑到你父亲外出威齐塔...
Her neighbor drove her, on account of your father was away on business...
...做生意的情况
...in Wichita.
你早产了一个星期   不过非常顺利
You were born a week early, but there were no complications.
接生非常成功. 你父亲很遗憾没在场
It was a perfect delivery. Your father was sorry not to be there.
不过那时男人都不进产房...
But it wasn't the custom then for men to be in the room for deliveries...
...所以我不明白他在场的话会有多少不同
...so I can't see how it would've been much different had he been there.
那就是你出生的真实故事
And that's the real story of how you were born.
不是很有意思   对吗?
Not very exciting, is it?
我只能在真实的版本...
And I suppose if I had to choose between the true version...
...和关於鱼和婚戒的精美故事...
...and an elaborate one involving a fish and a wedding ring...
...做出选择
...I might choose the fancy version.
但是   那是我
But, then that's just me.
我喜欢的版本
I kind of liked your version.
爸爸?
Dad?
嘿   爸爸? 嘿  你要我去叫护士?
Hey, Dad? Hey, you want me to get the nurse?
你要什么? 我能做什么? 要我拿什么?
What do you want? What can I do? What can I get?
你要喝水?
You want some water?
你要点水?
You want a bit of water?
河
The river.
河?
The river?
告诉我发生了什么
Tell me how it happens.
怎么发生的?
How what happens?
开始吧
How I go.
你的意思是当你看到那个眼睛的时候?
You mean what you saw in The Eye?
我不知道那个故事  爸爸. 你没告诉过我
I don't know that story, Dad. You never told me that one.
好. 嘿   好的   我试试
Okay. Hey, okay, I'll try.
我要你帮忙. 告诉我怎么开始
I need your help. Tell me how it starts.
像这样
Like this.
好的. 好的
Okay. Okay.
好的   在早上...
Okay, so it's in the morning...
...我和你在医院的时候睡着了. 我醒来...
...and you and I are in the hospital, and I've fallen asleep. And I wake up...
...看着你   你看上去好多了
...and I see you, and somehow you're better.
爸爸?
Dad?
你不一样了
You're different.
-爸爸 -我们离开这吧
- Dad. - Let's get out of here.
我说:
Then I say:
爸爸   你不能--
Dad, you're in no condition...
把轮椅拿来
Get that wheelchair.
快!我们没多少时间了!
Hurry up! We haven't much time!
一旦下了楼   我们就畅通无阻了
Once we get off this floor, we're in the clear.
我们坐上轮椅...
And we get in the wheelchair...
-快点! -...就像我们在逃离医院一样
- Faster! ...like we're escaping the hospital.
你在干什么?
What are you doing?
我们绕过了本耐特大夫   他想拦住我们
We pass Dr. Bennett, who tries to slow us down.
-拦住他们! -我们飞奔过大厅
- Stop them! - We're flying down the hall.
保安在追我们
Orderly after orderly is chasing us.
妈妈和傑瑟芬在最后
Mom and Josephine are at the end.
没有时间解释了! 拦住他们!
No time to explain! Stall them!
我们飞奔过围栏...
We come flying out over the curb...
...你的旧款红色车停在那. 不过很新. 崭新的
...and your old red Charger is there. But it's new. Brand-new.
我带你上去...
And I pick you up...
...你几乎没什么重量. 我不能解释
...and somehow you hardly weigh anything. I can't explain it.
离开! 我们不需要!
Leave it! We don't need it!
水. 我要喝水
Water. I need water.
-我们去哪? -河那里
- Where are we going? - The river.
我们走格伦镇这条路避免交通拥挤...
And we have to take Glenville to avoid traffic...
...因为去教堂的人开的很慢
...because the damn church people drive too slow.
我们越来越接近河...
And as we get close to the river...
他在那!
He's here!
...我们看见所有人都在那
...we see that everybody is already there.
我的意思是...
And I mean...
...所有人
...everyone.
太不可思议了
It's unbelievable.
我生命的故事
The story of my life.
奇怪的是   他们看上去并不生气
The strange thing is, there's not a sad face to be found.
每个人都很高兴见到你...
Everyone is just so glad to see you...
...为你送行
...and send you off right.
大家再见! 别了! 再见!
Goodbye, everybody! Farewell! Adieu!
我河里的姑娘
My girl in the river.
你变回到了原来的你
You become what you always were.
一条大鱼
A very big fish.
就是这么发生的
And that's how it happens.
对
Yeah.
太对了
Exactly.
妈妈?
Mom?
我的牧师做了主   我不能再要求什么了
The Lord is my shepherd, I shall not be in want.
他让我躺在碧绿的草地里
He makes me to lie down in green pastures.
在清清的河水边
He leads me beside the quiet waters.
他保留了我的灵魂
He restores my soul.
他用他的名义引导我走向公正
He guides me in the paths of righteousness for his name's sake.
对   我走过了死亡的阴影...
Yea, though I walk through the valley of the shadow of death...
...不再害怕恶魔   因为你和我在一起
...I will fear no evil, for you are with me.
善良和爱在我生命中的每一天
Surely goodness and love will follow me all the days of my life.
你听到过那种听了几遍都不知道哪好笑的笑话吗?
Have you ever heard a joke so many times you've forgotten why it's funny?
当你再听一遍觉得又是一个新的笑话
And then you hear it again and suddenly it's new.
你记得为什么第一次会喜欢它
You remember why you loved it in the first place.
他说他会和一个身高15英尺的巨人作战!
So he said he'll fight the giant who was 15 feet tall!
-没门! -爸爸! 那是真的   对吗?
- No way! - Dad! That's right, isn't it?
太对了
Pretty much.
瞧? 他确实是个巨人
See? So he was a giant.
我猜那是我父亲最后的笑话
That was my father's final joke, I guess.
一个讲了无数故事的人最终成了故事的一部分
A man tells his stories so many times that he becomes the stories.
故事在他死后继续流传
They live on after him.
从这方面来看   他永远不死
And in that way, he becomes immortal.